"Keep Out. -Birdman"
No response, eh?
応答なしと…
There are no pedals. It looks like a glider.
ペダルは　ありませんね　滑空専門のようです
No matter. Let us make it our jurisdiction regardless of its lack of wheels.
まあ　いいだろう
車輪がなくとも　われわれの専門内としよう
My shadowy business role is as the Master Sergeant of the Cheery Cycle Cleanup Corps.
わたしの裏稼業は　自転車整理軍の曹長
I sell off illegally parked bicycles,
違法駐輪自転車は売り飛ばし
and am using that as the basis for forming my gorgeous rose-colored campus life.
ゴージャスな　ばら色のキャンパスライフを　築く礎となる
Delicious sake, food, women flocking to me...
うまい酒と　食べ物と　寄ってくる女たち
The business may have a bit of a bad reputation,
多少　稼業の聞こえは悪いが　悪党ほど栄えるのが世の常だ
but the way of the world is the greater villainy, the greater glory.
I'll have my pick of raven-haired maidens...
黒髪の乙女など　より取り見取り
As long as I have the money, I can have anything I want!
金さえあれば　どうにでもなるのだ
Master Sergeant, a woman from Birdman is coming this way!
曹長！　バードマンの女が　こっちへ向かってるようです
What, some woman?
何だ　女か
Hey, what's the matter?
おい　どうした？
We're almost to Lake Biwa!
琵琶湖まで　あと少しだ
So it was you, Senpai.
先輩だったんですね
あ…　明石さん
Akashi-san...
That's the plane that we all made together!
あれは　わたしたちが作った飛行機です
Oh, is it?
えっ？　そうなんだ
It can be sold for a high price to a certain important person in the north.
北のさる要人に　高く売れるんだ
If you make an even better plane,
we could sell it for even more money.
もっと　いい飛行機を作れば　高い金で買ってやることもできる
So how about I become your sponsor?
何なら　スポンサーに　なってあげてもいい
You are an idiot!
先輩は　アホです
And what of it?
何　どうってことはない
This world is all a power game, after all.
しょせん　世の中　パワーゲーム
There is no such thing as pure love.
純愛など存在しない
Love is nothing but a fleeting illusion.
愛など　ひとときの夢幻にすぎん
Realize the truth about society, everyone!
皆　社会の真実を知れ
There is nothing in this world that cannot be bought with money!
金で買えぬものなど　この世にないのだ
Then what is this pain I feel in my heart?
しかし　心が痛むのは　なぜか
hitobito wa atsui kumo ni kao wo kakushiteru
人々は厚い雲で顔を隠してる
Humans hide their faces in front of thick clouds
iki ba no nai omoi wo zutto motte toideiru
行き場のない想いをずっと持って研いでいる
Getting more and more consumed by the feeling of getting nowhere
nani mo nai machi ni umorete mo sore demo ima demo
何もない街に埋もれても それでも 今でも
Even now, they're still buried in the same empty town
tsuranaru uindou ni
連なるウィンドウに
A perfect dream of dolls lined up
narabitatsu ningyou no marui yume
並び立つ人形の悪い夢
on a stretched out window
sore to mo soko ni kakurete
それとも倉庫に隠れて
Then they hide themselves away
fusaidetatte
塞いでたって
so that they can be covered up
hokori dake kabutte mitsukaranai
埃だけ被って見つからない
Wearing only their pride, they still can't find anything
dare no te ni datte furerarenai
誰の手にだって触れられない
They still aren't touched, no matter whose hands they're in
boku tachi no genzai wo kurikaesu koto darake demo
僕たちの現在を繰り返すことだらけでも
If we repeat this moment of ours properly,
sou itsuka kimi to deaou
そういつか君と出会おう
I will meet you someday
sonna hi wo omotte hibi wo ikou
そんな日を思って 日々を行こう
Until that day is here, I will keep on going
ikou
行こう
Going
Then I was a brand-spanking new freshman university student
当時ぴかぴかの大学１回生だったわたしの目の前には
and before me lay open innumerable doors to that rose-colored campus life.
ばら色のキャンパスライフへの扉が　無数に開かれていた
But I had already come to my decision.
しかし　わたしは　もはや　決死の覚悟であった
Among the many fliers, only one was conspicuous.
数あるチラシの中でも　ひときわ異彩を放つ　このチラシ
It's sink or swim!
イチかバチか
"Secret Society
Lucky Cat
Chinese Restaurant"
You can learn the other sides of a lot of different people.
いろんな人の裏側を　知ることができて
面白い経験　できるよ
It'll be a fun experience.
Um, what does "Secret Society" mean?
あの…　秘密機関というのは？
It means what it says.
その名のとおりさ
Manager, we have a prospective new hire!
店長　入店希望者です
Here.
どうぞ
I am Aijima, the manager of Lucky Cat Chinese Restaurant. Nice to meet you.
福猫飯店の店長　相島だ　よろしく
Please read this now.
あと　これ読んで
I didn't actually expect an organization that wrote "Secret Society" on their flier
まさか　「秘密機関」と　大々的に　チラシに書く秘密機関が
to actually be a secret society,
but the Lucky Cat Chinese Restaurant is one, exactly as the sign said.
あるわけないと思っていたが　福猫飯店は
看板に偽りなく　秘密機関なのであった
Their branches include the Library Police, the Print Shop,
下部組織に　図書館警察　印刷所　自転車にこやか整理軍
the Cheery Cycle Cleanup Corps, and a bunch of other unofficial circles...
その他　有象無象の　非公認サークルを
Taken all together, they are the Lucky Cat Chinese Restaurant.
ひっくるめて「福猫飯店」といった
In other words, they have a hand in all the business at the school,
つまりは　学校中の裏稼業を　一手に引き受け
and is the organization that essentially controls the university.
大学を　裏でコントロールしている組織
That is the Lucky Cat Chinese Restaurant.
それが　福猫飯店
And there you have it.
というわけだ　ゲエッ！
By the way, once you've read the menu you will not be allowed to quit our organization.
ちなみに　読んだ以上　わが組織を　やめることは許されない
If you do quit the shop,
もし　店をやめれば　お勘定という　社会的抹殺手段が待っている
a little process called "paying the bill" will be waiting to erase you from society.
We gather every single piece of personal information about the students.
われわれは　学生たちの　ありとあらゆる個人情報を網羅している
Which videos you rented from the video rental store,
君がレンタルビデオ店で何を借りたか
what you bought from the supermarket or convenience store,
スーパー　コンビニでは　何を買ったか
which books you read, which transmissions you sent...
どんな本を読み
何を送受信したか
Even what you smelled like when you were a baby.
子供のころは　どんなにおいのする赤ちゃんだったかなど
We know it all.
全ては　お見通しであるぞ
But I had no intention of turning back!
とはいえ　わたしは　引くつもりは　なかった
This is perfect.
上等だ
この福猫飯店で　上り詰めてみせる
I will show them all by climbing to the top of this Lucky Cat Chinese Restaurant!
That's a good look you've got there.
いい顔だ
For now I will assign you to the Library Police.
ひとまず　君には　図書館警察に所属してもらう
Glad to have you on board.
よろしく
There stood an ominous man with an evil face of ill portent.
そこには　ひどく　縁起の　悪そうな顔をした　不気味な男
And that man has made a giant plaything out of my fate ever since.
この男が　後に　わたしの運命を
大きく翻弄することに　なろうとは
The original aim of the Library Police
図書館警察本来の目的は
図書館から借りた図書を　返却しない不届き者を追い詰め
was to chase down the scoundrels who had not returned materials to the library
and to recover the lent books by force.
貸し出し図書を　力ずくで回収することであった
However, the goal eventually deviated from how it had started,
しかし　回収の手だてであった　延滞者の情報収集が
and most people's secret and personal information
当初の目的を逸脱し
北は大原三千院から
were accumulated by the Library Police--
南は宇治の平等院鳳凰堂まで　及んだ暁には
people both inside and outside of Kyoto, from Oohara's Sanzen Temple in the north
to Uiji's Byoudou Temple's Houou Hall in the south.
らく中らく外　ほとんどの人物の　秘密
個人的情報が　図書館警察に蓄積され
It's now even an organization that helps participate in politics.
Indeed, those who control information, control the world.
今では　政治にまで　関与できる組織になっていた
I will rise in rank,
まさに　情報を制したものが　世界を制す
and get to a place where I can handle all the information I want!
組織内で出世し　思うがままに　情報を扱える立場になるのだ
However, I quickly ran into a strange individual whom I was to collect from.
しかし　わたしは　いきなり
奇妙な人物の取り立てに　当たってしまった
Higuchi Seitarou, that's enough!
樋口　清太郎！　いいかげんにしろ！
That copy of Jules Verne's 20,000 Leagues Under the Sea is more than a year overdue!
ジュール·ヴェルヌの　『海底二万海里』を
１年近く延滞しているぞ！
Do your duty as a library patron!
利用者の責務を果たせ！
Higuchi-san, it's way past the due date, you know.
樋口さん　期限は　とっくに過ぎてるんですよ
Yes, it is... But just a little longer...
そうだよね　でも　もうちょっとなんだ
It's already been four months since you said that!
そう言ってから　もう　４カ月になりますよ
Has it?
そうだっけ
Gotta hit the john.
ちょっと　かわやへ
And so, unable to collect a single book for more than a year,
そうして　たった１冊の本を
１年間　取り立てられなかった
I won fame as the greatest failure in the history of the Library Police.
わたしは　図書館警察史上　空前の落ちこぼれという勇名をはせた
On the other hand, Ozu used all kinds of techniques
反対に　小津は　あらゆる技巧を凝らし
to recover books from the evil overduers and was promoted for it.
悪質な延滞者から　次々と　図書を回収し　出世していった
さらには　不可思議な人脈を広げ続け
Furthermore, he spun an unfathomable web of human connections,
and rose even in his first year to become the right hand man to Aijima-senpai.
１回生ながら　相島先輩の右腕　というべき存在に成り上がった
Damn it! Why does a human like you end up being promoted?
チクショー
お前のような人間が　なぜ　出世するのだ？
非の打ちどころのない人柄
An unimpeachable character, conversational skills, clear thinking,
巧みな話術
明晰な頭脳
a cute appearance, and copious amounts of overflowing love for your fellow man.
かわいらしい容ぼう
こんこんと　あふれて　尽きることのない隣人への愛
Those are the secrets to being loved by others.
人から愛される秘訣は　これです
Shut up! I'll kill you, you bastard!
黙れ！　ぶち殺すぞ！
I don't want to live some meaningless life enjoying the unhappiness of others!
人の不幸を楽しんでいるだけの　無意義な暮らしなど　いらん
I want to be promoted!
わたしは出世したいのだ！
You are so very awkward.
不器用な人だなあ
Why don't you have more fun?
もっと　楽しんではいかが？
After all, no matter how hard you work, I'll do my best to make sure you turn out no good.
まっ　どんなに　あなたが頑張ろうと
僕は　全力で　あなたを駄目にします
わたしたちは　どす黒い糸で結ばれているというわけです
"Philippine Trench"
We are tied together by a dark thread, you see.
It wasn't until far later that I came to understand
樋口氏の姑息な逃亡に　小津が裏で　関与していると
分かったのは　ずいぶん　後の話であった
that Mr. Higuchi's impromptu escapes were aided by Ozu.
You're getting in the way, you bastard?
貴様　俺の邪魔をしているのか？
すいません　あの人は　僕の師匠なんですわ
Sorry. He's my Master.
Please overlook it.
これで　大目に見てやってください
"Brand New"
You think that'll cut it?
そんなわけに　いくか！
June of my second year, finally realizing I had no talent at collecting books,
２回生の６月
いよいよ　図書回収の才覚なしと　判断された
わたしは　印刷所へと異動になった
the "restaurant" transferred me to the Print Shop.
The Print Shop is an organization in control of many excellent students
印刷所は　たくさんの　優秀な学生たちを従え
偽造リポートを量産している　組織である
which mass produces fraudulent reports.
Always at hand to save students facing a crisis,
学生たちが困ったときに　急場をしのぐ手だてであり
my job was to deliver the finished reports to the customers.
わたしの職務は上がったリポートを顧客に受け渡す仕事であった
In order to get promoted faster,
I took on a large number of customers,
わたしは　少しでも出世を早めるべく
営業によって顧客を大量に獲得し　トラックでリポートを配送していた
delivering reports using a truck.
Thanks, come again.
毎度
Thanks to that incident, over 200 students failed credits.
この事件で
顧客二百余名が　単位を落としてしまうという
It was the worst disaster in the history of the Print Shop, and it lost the customers' faith.
印刷所始まって以来の　信用を落とす　惨事を起こしてしまった
Since I was an acquaintance of Ozu, he couldn't be so obvious about it,
小津の知り合いであるため　あからさまに　態度には出さないが
but Aijima-senpai had been putting more and more distance between us.
だんだん　わたしから　距離を置いていた　相島先輩が
He then spoke to me suddenly.
珍しく　声を掛けてきた
I have a side job. Help out.
バイトだ　手伝え
Aijima-senpai's front
相島先輩の表の顔は　図書委員長と
was the President of the library and supervisor of the Movie Circle Misogi.
映画サークル　「ＭＩＳＯＧＩ」を主宰する
城ヶ崎氏のたいこ持ちであった
He was the jester in Mr. Jougasaki's court.
Our mission was to collect information on a new recruit and allow him to approach her.
われわれのミッションは　ある新入生の情報を探り
先輩を接近させることであった
Hey, what do you do on the weekends, Akashi-san?
ねえ　明石さんは　休みの日　何してんの？
何で　そんなこと　先輩に　言わないといけないのですか？
Why do I have to tell you something like that, Senpai?
Hurry and go search!
早く探ってこい
R-Right!
あっ　はい
ガ　ガ　ガが…
M-M-M-M-M-Mo...
They're called Mochiguman and they come in sets of five...
５匹揃って　モチグマンというのですが
Oh? One's missing...
あれ　１匹いない
Now that you mention it, I think something flew off when you fell...
そういえば　転げた拍子に　何か飛んでいったような
Don't, it's dangerous. It's okay.
いえ　危ないですから
大丈夫です
あっ　しかし
But...
I don't know why, but it's always come back to me, even if I didn't search for it.
昔から　捜さなくても　なぜだか　必ず戻ってきますので
I, having broken Aijima-senpai's mood, was demoted to the Cheery Cycle Cleanup Corps.
相島先輩の　機嫌を損ねた　わたしは
自転車にこやか整理軍へと　左遷された
The Cheery Cycle Cleanup Corps is a group that manages the illegal parking of bicycles,
自転車にこやか整理軍とは
違法駐輪自転車を取り締まる　団体であり
福猫飯店の　大きな財源となっている
and is a major source of funds for the Lucky Cat Chinese Restaurant.
You weak-kneed wimp! Get it together!
この　へっぴり腰が！　しっかりしろ！
This organization does not suit my talents.
この組織は　わたしの才能に　見合ってないのだ
I'm thinking of revealing Aijima and all the crimes
いっそ　福猫飯店史上に　残るほどの犯行を　相島に示して
the Lucky Cat Chinese Restaurant has committed through the years and escaping...
逃亡してやろうと思う
That's dangerous. You'll end up like this.
危ないな
こんなふうに　なっちゃいますよ
"Squish"
Not like you give a damn.
へとも思わんくせに
Even now I'm using brilliant maneuvers to cover for you, you know.
今だって　僕が　天才的な立ち回りを見せて
かばってあげているんですよ
Try being a little grateful.
少しは　感謝していただきたいものです
感謝なんかするものか！
Grateful? Hell no!
Aijima-senpai is definitely trouble, yes...
確かに　相島先輩は困り者ですが
Interested in this?
これ　気になりますか？
Not really... Though, where did you get it?
いや
ちなみに　それは　どこで？
I searched it out using the information network of the Library Police.
図書館警察の情報網を使って　捜させたんですよ
Since Akashi-san said she lost it.
明石さんが　なくしたっていうもんだから
I followed the clues, but it was quite the struggle.
足取りを追うのに苦労しました
Almost like it was wandering around trying to be picked up by someone.
まるで　誰かに拾われるのを求めてさまよってたみたいに
Oh, pardon me.
おっと　失礼
I'm so very busy playing the game of love!
恋に遊びに大忙しですわ
Hello? Yes...
もしもし　はいはい
W-Wait, I can't just... So suddenly...
ちょっと　そんなこと　急に言われても
This is the dutch wife we're targeting.
これが　ターゲットの　ダッチワイフだ
Jougasaki has named it Kaori, and we're going to take it from him!
城ヶ崎は　香織と呼んでいるが　これを強奪する
In order to earn the respect of Akashi-san,
例の明石さんから　尊敬を得るために
相島先輩は　城ヶ崎氏を　陥れることに決めたのだ
Aijima-senpai decided to play a prank on Mr. Jougasaki.
Many people know of the depressing things called "Dutch Wives" in this world. Even I knew.
世の中に　ダッチワイフと呼ばれる
切ないものがあることは　多くの人が知っていよう
わたしだって知っていた
But what is this elegant expression Kaori-san has?
しかし　この香織さんの　気品ある表情は　どうであろう
This is not the face that speaks out to the corrupt morals of society.
決して　背徳的な生活に　うつつを抜かす顔ではない
The carefully combed hair, the exquisitely prepared dress....
丁寧に　なでつけられた髪も
きちんと整えられた　上品な衣服も
They showed the depth of Mr. Jougasaki's love.
城ヶ崎氏の　愛の深さを示している
Can I, as a human being, allow the delicate and subtle world these two created to be destroyed?
この２人が　つくり上げた　繊細　微妙な世界を
ぶち壊すことは
人として許されるのか
No, it is the height of heresy...
いや　まさに外道の極み
Kidnapping Kaori-san and using her to threaten Mr. Jougasaki I will not allow!
香織さんを誘拐し　城ヶ崎氏を　脅迫するなど言語道断なり
I cannot let this happen! It is a very refined, pure love!
これは犯してはいけない　高尚な純愛である
Sickening...
ウエッ　気色悪い
生きていない人形をめでるなど　理解できんな
I can't understand loving some doll that's not alive.
He even put lipstick on her!
オホホッ　口紅までつけて
やめろ！
Enough!
Stepping on other people's pure love for the sake of your own desire is unacceptable!
自分の恋路のために　人の純愛を　踏みにじるなど言語同断！
これは　公私混同された　ミッションだ
You're letting your private desires influence your public missions!
彼女に触れることは許さん！
I will not allow you to lay a finger on her!
Of course I did not say that.
もちろん　そんなことは言えず
I instead chose a strategic withdrawal.
わたしは　戦略的撤退の道を選んだ
I'm not going to be a part of something so stupid!
こんなアホなことするもんか！
I had finally gone and done it.
とうとう　やってしまった
I will surely be erased from society by Aijima's power...
今度こそ　わたしは相島の力によって
社会的に　抹殺されてしまうだろう
You have nothing to worry about.
何　心配はいりません　万事　うまくいきますよ
Things are going quite well.
Anyway, opportunity is always dangling in front of your eyes. Please grab onto it.
とにかく　好機は　いつでも
あなたの目の前に　ぶら下がってございます
それを　つかまえてごらんなさい
That'll be 9,000 yen.
はい　９，０００円
That's almost 5 figures!
大台に近い！
I ran and hid in a manga café on Kitashira River, shaking like a newborn fawn.
わたしは　そのまま　北白川の漫画喫茶へ逃げ込み
生まれたての子ジカのように　ぷるぷると恐怖に震えていた
But no one came after me, and a week afterward Aijima-senpai lost his standing.
しかし　追っ手が来ることはなく
わたしが　相島先輩の失脚を知ったのは
逃亡から１週間後であった
"New Hero -- Bra-man!"
"Aijima Bra-man!"
"Stop the Filming!"
"Animal Abuse!"
"Lipstick Licker!"
"Watch out for the ladies' locker room!"
"Spits in your tea!"
"Crazy Fetishist! Panty Sniffer!"
Oh, long time no see.
あら　お久しぶり
I've become the Manager of the Lucky Cat Chinese Restaurant.
僕　福猫飯店の　店長になっちゃったんですよ
This was your doing?
お前が仕込んだのか？
Now now, don't give me a bad reputation.
嫌だな　人聞きの悪い
相島先輩が　組織を私物化してるから
Aijima-senpai was running the organization for his personal use,
so I spoke with the executive board of the Lucky Cat Chinese Restaurant.
福猫飯店の幹部の方々に　お声をお掛けしたんです
I was vaguely apprehensive.
わたしは　空恐ろしくなった
What else could I be but a Renaissance man of fear?
恐るべき　八面六臂ぶりというほかない
So, will you help me?
どうです　手伝ってくれませんか？
Don't you think it's about time you take this lucky chance to enjoy life?
いいかげん　ええ目を見ても　ええのんとちゃいますの？
"Ozu Establishes his Government"
Master Sergeant!
曹長！
And so I assumed the office of the Master Sergeant of the Cheery Cycle Cleanup Corps.
そうして　わたしは　自転車にこやか整理軍の　曹長に就任した
At first I was somewhat skeptical of this activity,
最初は　その活動に懐疑的であったが
but I became more and more absorbed in it,
次第に　のめり込み
不毛に過ぎた　２年間の遅れを取り戻すべく　熱心に指揮を振るった
directing it with a passion to take back the two previous years that had gone wasted.
The organization acted exactly as I desired. It felt quite good, actually.
組織が自分の思いどおりに　動くのは　実に気分がいい
これが　望んでいた　ばら色の　キャンパスライフかもしれない
This might be that rose-colored campus life I wished for.
A cornucopia of raven-haired maidens to choose from!
黒髪の乙女も選び放題
Could this be my ideal?
まさに　理想的ではないか
It was no easy task getting here.
ここまでの道のりは　楽ではなかった
But I had finally obtained it.
しかし　とうとう手に入れた
"Go!"
"Get a move on!"
It was all too easy to grasp once I tried!
手にしてみれば　あっけないが　世の中　そういうものだ
I had once been led astray by an adherence to pure love.
昔は　純愛というものに固執して　人生を見まごうところだった
But I finally realized. Everything in this world revolved around money!
しかし　ようやく分かった
世の中の全ては　金で動いているのだ
Master Sergeant, I have something excellent to tell you of.
曹長！　いい話があるんですが
It will be quite profitable.
これが良い収入になるかと
Is there something like that?
あるのか？
There's something in the Birdman Club.
へい　バードマンクラブにいいのが
And that was the result, as you clearly saw.
で　ご覧のとおりの　結果であった
I should have had everything I wanted. Did I make a mistake somewhere, somehow?
全て　手に入れたはずの　わたしであったが
どこで　何を　間違えてしまったというのか
You! I have finished! I'm finished!
貴君　終わったよ　終わった
Finished with what?
何が終わったんです？
This. This morning I finished my journey of more than two years.
これだよ
２年以上にわたる旅が　けさ　終わった
あんまり感激したので　貴君に伝えようと思ったんだ
I was so moved I wanted to tell you about it.
At this point? Why...
今ごろ　そんな
I'm sorry I took so long.
長いこと悪かったね
But it was some good times, indeed.
でも　いい時間を　過ごさせてもらった
I am hungry. Would you like to go eat some ramen?
腹が減っているんだ　ラーメンでも食べに行かないか？
Speaking of which, when I left the university a few days ago I ran into an old friend.
そういえば　先日　大学へ出掛けたら
They were not looking so comfortable at all, and hurried off somewhere.
昔の友人に会ってね　向こうは　えらく気まずそうな顔をして
そそくさと　どこかへ行ってしまった
If they're in the same year as you, Master, they're probably a doctoral student now.
師匠と　同回生だったら
その人は　大学院の博士課程でしょう
No wonder they felt awkward.
そりゃ　気まずい思いにもなります
Why would they be embarrassed?
なぜ　向こうが恥ずかしがる？
It's not them who had to repeat classes.
留年するのは　向こうじゃあるまいし
And that is the very reason you are the Master, indeed.
そこが　師匠の　師匠たるゆえんですかね
I've thought about this for quite a while, but now my mind is made up.
前々から考えてはいたんだが　決心が固まった
It will soon be the day for me to go forth, out into the world.
そろそろ　わたしも　世界に乗り出す日が来たようだ
I will circle the globe.
世界を回ってくるよ
Sounds like fun.
楽しそうですね
I feel like something went awry with my life.
わたしは　何だか　人生を誤った気がします
Your life has not yet begun.
貴君は　まだ　人生が始まってもいない
You are spending overtime inside of your mother's belly.
ここは　まだ　ご母堂のおなかの延長だぞ
It's not that bad.
悪くはないんです
I successfully obtained a life that people would be jealous of.
人もうらやむような　人生の成功を手に入れた
But something is missing.
でも　何か　物足りない
Is this really it?
こんなものだったのかと　あるいは
もっと　有意義な人生が　あったかもしれない
There's got to be some more meaningful life out there...
More rose-colored, more sparkling!
もっと　ばら色で　もっと　光り輝いていて
There might have been some
一点の曇りもない学生生活を　思うさま　満喫していたかも
college life with not a single dark cloud that would have satisfied me!
What's the matter? Are you half asleep?
どうしたんだね　寝ぼけているのか？
I got to where I am by believing in my own potential!
わたしは　自分の可能性を信じて　ここまで　やってきました
どうにか　うまくいったけど　なぜだか　心が寒い
I'm not sure I'm saying it right...
But why does my heart feel so cold?
Maybe there's a choice I should have made that would have led to some other possibility?
わたしが選択すべきは　もっと別の可能性だったかも
Maybe the choices I made in my first year were wrong!
１回生のころに　選択を誤ったのかもしれない
You cannot use the word "possibility" without limitations.
可能性という言葉を　無限定に使ってはいけない
Can you become a bunny girl?
君は　バニーガールになれるか？
Can you become a pilot?
パイロットになれるか？
アイドル歌手に
Can you become a famous singer, or a superhero who saves the world with his powers?
必殺技で　世界を救うヒーローになれるか？
No, I can't.
なれません
Perhaps you could.
なれるかもしれん
But if you keep focusing your gaze on that which is unrealistic, you never will.
しかし　ありもしないものに　目を奪われては　どうにもならん
The root of all your evil
自分の　ほかの可能性という　当てにならないものに
望みを託すことが諸悪の根源だ
is in always relying on one of your other possibilities to get your wish.
You must accept that you are the person here, now,
今　ここにいる君以外
ほかの何者にもなれない自分を　認めなくてはいけない
and that you cannot become anyone else other than that person.
There is no way that you can lead some worthwhile college life and feel satisfied.
君が有意義な学生生活を　満喫できるわけがない
I guarantee it, so have confidence!
わたしが保証するから　どっしり構えておれ
There is no such thing as that rose-colored campus life.
ばら色のキャンパスライフなど　存在せんのだ
Why? Because there is nothing rose-colored in this world.
なぜなら　世の中は　ばら色ではない
Everything is all a bunch of colors mixed up, you see.
実に　雑多な色をしているからね
Oh, what perfect timing, meeting you here!
おっ　いい所で　出会った　一杯　付き合え
How about a drink?
Well, that's your fault.
そりゃ　あんた　悪いわ
相島から逃げ出したとこまでは　カッコ良かったけどね
Although you were pretty cool until you ran away from Aijima-senpai.
I was fooled by Ozu.
わたしは　小津に　してやられたんです
If I hadn't met him, I wouldn't have completely wasted these two years.
小津と出会ってなければ
この２年間を　棒に振ることもなかった
He's selfish and arrogant, lazy and perverse...
あいつは　わがままで　傲慢　怠惰で　あまのじゃく
He eats people's unhappiness with three helpings of rice, and that's not all!
他人の不幸をおかずに　飯が　３杯　食えて　その上…
But his feelings are pure.
でも　純粋なのよね？
That's how Ozu-kun feels about his girlfriend.
小津君　あれで　彼女思いだからさ
G-Girlfriend?
かっ　彼女？
What was her name again?
名前　何てったっけ？
I could never believe that Ozu would have a girlfriend.
小津に彼女など　あり得ない
He said that he met her as a freshman in the tennis circle.
１回生のころ　テニスサークルで　知り合ったんだって
He went with her to see the Gozan festival,
五山を一緒に見に行ったけど
but they were tossed around in the crowd of people and she ended up crying.
人込みに　もまれて　見られないで　彼女が泣いちゃって
This year he plans to see all five mountains at once.
ことしは　五山を同時に見るつもりらしいよ
There isn't any place you can see all five at once from.
五山を同時に見られる場所など　ありません
空でも飛ばないかぎり
Not unless you're in the air...
Okay, that's enough!
はい　そこまで！
Who the hell are you people?
なっ　何よ　あんたたち！
Ozu used the members of the Lucky Cat Chinese Restaurant for his own personal uses.
小津は　福猫飯店の構成員を私的に動かしていた
He mixed up his private and public duties too!
やつこそ　とんだ公私混同だ
He's snuck into the Honwaka Group's headquarters
ほんわかの団体本部に忍び込み　そこの飛行船を盗むつもりだ
and is planning on stealing the airship there.
"Illegal Distribution of Funds"
"To Honwaka..."
It seems he hid his tracks, but I know he has a woman there.
ひた隠しにしていたようだが　女がいるのも分かった
"Steal Airship"
例の団体　ほんわかの娘だ
It's the daughter of the head of Honwaka Group.
He's planning on using that airship for a date.
飛行船で　デートを計画している
"Honwaka's Daughter?"
"You've got to be kidding me!"
This was indeed a bolt out of the blue.
それは　まさしく　青天のへきれきであった
Perhaps I had misjudged Ozu all this time.
わたしは　小津のことを　見誤っていたのかもしれない
Ozu has a girlfriend?
小津に彼女が？
Was his rise to the top all for such a pure reason?
そこまで上り詰めたのも　そんな純情な理由のためか？
His goal wasn't simply to spend his time meaninglessly?
無意義な暮らしぶりを　望んでいたのではなかったか！
He's taking off!
飛ぶぞ！
He plans to take off from here and pick up the girl in the facility on the next mountain over!
隣山の施設にいる　その娘を　ここから飛んで拾うつもりだ！
I won't let you!
そうは　させないよ
You, especially, I won't let you get your way!
君だけ　いい思いさせてなるものか
Shoot it down!
撃ち落とせ！
You are quite the persistent one!
あんたも　しつこい男ですね
I say the same to you!
お前に　その言葉は返したい！
Be more honest with yourself.
素直じゃないな
Transfer over!
乗り移れ！
Hey, not me!
こら　俺はいい！
Just a bit more...
もう少し
"Ozu had a girlfriend!"
It's crashed! Surround the area!
落ちた！　包囲しろ！
Everything I had done had all been meaningless,
これまで　わたしは　無意義な　暮らしぶりをしてきたが
but I had thought that it was the same for Ozu.
それは　小津も同じだと思っていた
However, Ozu had enjoyed his meaningless campus life to his heart's content,
しかし　小津は　無意義な学生生活を　力いっぱいエンジョイし
he had a girlfriend, and was even a fool in love!
彼女がいて　アホ並みの純愛度である
Was I the only one who wasted his life?
不毛なのは　わたしだけであったのか
Immediately after I was born, I was the incarnation of innocence.
生後　間もないころの　わたしは　純粋無垢の権化であり
Loved as much as baby Hikaru Genji was by Kaguya.
光源氏の赤子時代もかくやと　思われる　愛らしさ
邪念のかけらもない　その笑顔は
郷里の山野を　愛の光で満たしたといわれる
With not a hint of a wicked thought,
it was said my smile would illuminate the countryside around my hometown with the light of love.
それが　今は　どうであろう
And what of me now?
Is this how you plan to settle your accounts, as you are?
これが現時点における　お前の総決算だというのか
Where is the one responsible?
責任者は　どこか？
If it will always turn out like this, then I should do nothing at all!
どう　あがいても　こうなるなら
何もしないのが一番だ
It would be best not to set foot outside of the 4.5 tatami room!
四畳半から　一歩たりとも出ぬがよかろう
tengoku iku tame mainichi kosotto
天国　いくため　毎日こそっと
In order to go to heaven. Everyday, I quietly
naishou de ii koto shiteta kedo
内緒で　いいこと　してたけど
and privately do good deeds
namida hitohira
涙ひとひら
But a single teardrop
atama kurakura
あたまくらくら
Sends my head spinning
ano ko hasuppa koi dorobou
あの娘　はすっぱ　恋泥棒
That stupid girl, that love thief
watashi kenage ii hito
わたしけなげ　いいひと
I am a good and pure person
kanawanakatta koigokoro
叶わなかった恋心
My longing heart was not fulfilled
kamisama doushite
神様どうして
Why, god?
yurusanakucha koi dorobou
ゆるさなくっちゃ恋泥棒
I must forgive her. That love thief
ano ko tabun ii hito
あの娘たぶん　いいひと
Maybe she was actually a good person
wasurenakucha konna koto
忘れなくっちゃこんなこと
I have to forget all these things
watashi wa tengoku
わたしは天国
I'm in heaven
yurusanakucha
ゆるさなくっちゃ
I have to forgive her!